<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Root>
  <article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" dtd-version="3.0">
	  <!--This XML file has been marked up and exported from Adobe InDesign-->
	  <front>
		<article-meta>
			<title-group>
				<article-title>New species of the plesiomorphic genus  Nixonia Masner (Hymenoptera, Platygastroidea,  Platygastridae, Scelioninae) from South Africa</article-title>
			</title-group>
			 
			<contrib-group>
				<name>
					<given-names>Simon</given-names>
					<surname>van Noort</surname>
				</name>
				1,†, 
				<name>
					<given-names>Norman F.</given-names>
					<surname>Johnson</surname>
				</name>
				2,‡ 
				 1 
				<aff>Division of Natural History, Iziko South African Museum, PO Box 61, Cape Town, 8000, South Africa</aff> 
				 2 
				<aff>Department of Entomology, The Ohio State University, 1315 Kinnear Road, Columbus, Ohio 43212, U.S.A</aff> 
				 † <uri content-type="lsid">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:7CCD166F-F1FA-43DA-B582-4E84EAF59AD1</uri>
				 ‡ <uri content-type="lsid">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:3508C4FF-F027-445F-8417-90AB4AB8FE0D</uri> 
				 Corresponding author: Simon van Noort (
					<email>svannoort@iziko.org.za</email>
				)
			</contrib-group>
			 Academic editor: Norman F. Johnson  |  Received 24 February 2009  |  Accepted 8 July 2009  |  Published 
			<pub-date>
				<day>14</day>
				<month>September</month> 
				<year>2009</year>
				 
			</pub-date>
			<uri content-type="lsid">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:A8B61739-D1BF-426C-A3BE-D51E7717A6AC</uri>
			 Citation: van Noort S, Johnson NF (2009) New species of the plesiomorphic genus Nixonia Masner (Hymenoptera, Platygastroidea, Platygastridae, Scelioninae) from South Africa. In: Johnson N (Ed) Advances in the sys­tematics of Hymenoptera. Festschrift in honour of Lubomír Masner. ZooKeys 
			<issue>20</issue>: 
			<fpage>31</fpage>–
			<lpage>51</lpage>. 
			<uri content-type="doi">doi: 10.3897/zookeys.20.112</uri>
			 
			<permissions>
				<copyright-statement>Copyright S. van Noort &amp; N.F. Johnson. This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</copyright-statement>
			</permissions>
			<abstract>Abstract 
				<p>Two new species of 
					<taxon-name>Nixonia</taxon-name> 
					Masner (
					<taxon-name>Hymenoptera</taxon-name>
					, <taxon-name>Platygastridae</taxon-name>, 
					<taxon-name>Scelioninae</taxon-name>), 
					<taxon-name>Nixonia masneri</taxon-name> 
					<bold>sp. n.</bold> and 
					<taxon-name>Nixonia mcgregori</taxon-name> 
					<bold>sp. n.</bold> are described from South Africa and further records of <taxon-name>Nixonia corrugata</taxon-name> Johnson &amp; Masner, <taxon-name>Nixonia lamorali</taxon-name> Johnson &amp; Masner, <taxon-name>Nixonia stygica</taxon-name> Johnson &amp; Masner are documented. Johnson and Masner’s 2006 identification key is modified to include the newly described species. Online interactive Lucid matrix and Lucid Phoenix dichotomous keys are available on WaspWeb at <ext-link xlink:href="http://www.waspweb.org/Platygastroidea/Keys/index.htm.">http://www.waspweb.org/Platygastroidea/Keys/index.htm.</ext-link> Lucid data files in lif and sdd format are available at: <ext-link xlink:href="doi:10.3897/zookeys.20.112.app.1.ik">doi:10.3897/zookeys.20.112.app.1.ik</ext-link> and <ext-link xlink:href="doi:10.3897/zookeys.20.112.app.2.ik">doi:10.3897/zookeys.20.112.app.2.ik</ext-link>.</p></abstract> <kwd-group>Keywords <kwd>Holotype</kwd>, <kwd>Hymenoptera</kwd>, <kwd>identification key</kwd>, <kwd>new species</kwd>, <kwd>lucid keys</kwd>, <kwd>Nixonia</kwd>, <kwd>Platygastridae</kwd>, <kwd>South Africa</kwd>, <kwd>Scelioninae</kwd>, <kwd>taxonomy</kwd></kwd-group> </article-meta>
	</front>
	<body>
		<sec sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title> <p>The genus <taxon-name>Nixonia</taxon-name> was for a long time only known from two species, <taxon-name>Nixonia pretiosa</taxon-name> Masner (Namibia) and <taxon-name>Nixonia atra</taxon-name> Masner (Angola, Democratic Republic of Congo, <!-- page break --> Kenya, Malawi, Rwanda, Zimbabwe) (<xref rid="B7">Masner 1958</xref>, <xref rid="B8">1970</xref>). More recently twelve additional species were described (<xref rid="B5">Johnson and Masner 2006</xref>): <taxon-name>Nixonia bini</taxon-name> (Somalia); <taxon-name>Nixonia corrugata</taxon-name> (South Africa); <taxon-name>Nixonia elongata</taxon-name> (South Africa); <taxon-name>Nixonia flavocincta</taxon-name> (Namibia); <taxon-name>Nixonia gigas</taxon-name> (South Africa); <taxon-name>Nixonia krombeini</taxon-name> (India, Laos, Sri Lanka, Thailand, Vietnam); <taxon-name>Nixonia lamorali</taxon-name> (South Africa); <taxon-name>Nixonia pecki</taxon-name> (Botswana, South Africa, Zimbabwe); <taxon-name>Nixonia priesneri</taxon-name> (Egypt); <taxon-name>Nixonia sicaria</taxon-name> (Namibia); <taxon-name>Nixonia stygica</taxon-name> (South Africa); <taxon-name>Nixonia watshami</taxon-name> (Botswana, Namibia, Zimbabwe). The only host record for the genus is for <taxon-name>N. watshami</taxon-name>, which been reared from the eggs of <taxon-name>Acanthoplus discoidalis</taxon-name> (Walker) (<taxon-name>Orthoptera</taxon-name>: <taxon-name>Tettigoniidae</taxon-name>, <taxon-name>Hetrodinae</taxon-name>) in Botswana and Namibia (<xref rid="B5">Johnson and Masner 2006</xref>).</p> <p>Prior to the recent implementation of an intensive inventory survey program near Nieuwoudtville under the auspices of the PBI <taxon-name>Platygastroidea</taxon-name> project, a total of 121 <taxon-name>Nixonia</taxon-name> specimens representing 14 species were known, 77 of these specimens belonging to two widely distributed species and seven species only known from singletons (<xref rid="B5">Johnson and Masner 2006</xref>). During the first two months of sampling in the Hantam National Botanical Gardens near Nieuwoudtville, 39 specimens (10 females, 29 males) of a new species related to <taxon-name>N. gigas</taxon-name> and 5 specimens (2 females and 3 males) of <taxon-name>N. corrugata</taxon-name> were collected, illustrating the historical lack of intensive sampling in the right places at the right time (<xref rid="B17">van Noort 2008</xref>). </p> <p>A further undescribed <taxon-name>Nixonia</taxon-name> species related to <taxon-name>N. lamorali</taxon-name> emerged from processing of samples collected in Kogelberg Biosphere Reserve (50km east of Cape Town). This species may usurp <taxon-name>N. gigas</taxon-name> as the largest <taxon-name>Nixonia</taxon-name>, and is appropriately named in honour of Lubomír Masner, the doyen of platygastroid taxonomy. Here we describe these two new species, modify the existing key (<xref rid="B5">Johnson and Masner 2006</xref>) and provide links to online versions of the key.</p> </sec> <sec sec-type="materials-methods"><title>Materials and methods</title> <p>Classification follows <xref rid="B16">Sharkey (2007)</xref> who synonymised the family <taxon-name>Scelionidae</taxon-name> with <taxon-name>Platygastridae</taxon-name> based on the phylogenetic analysis of <xref rid="B12">Murphy et al. (2007)</xref>. <taxon-name>Platygastroidea</taxon-name> currently comprises the single family <taxon-name>Platygastridae</taxon-name> containing five subfamilies: <taxon-name>Platygastrinae</taxon-name>; <taxon-name>Sceliotrachelinae</taxon-name>, <taxon-name>Scelioninae</taxon-name>, <taxon-name>Teleasinae</taxon-name> and <taxon-name>Telenominae</taxon-name>.</p> <p>Images were produced using the EntoVision micro-imaging system. This system included a Leica M16 zoom lens attached to a JVC KY-75U 3-CCD digital video camera that fed image data to a notebook computer. The program Cartograph 5.6.0 was then used to merge an image series into a single in focus image. Lighting was achieved using techniques summarized in <xref rid="B2">Buffington et al. (2005)</xref>, <xref rid="B6">Kerr et al. (2009)</xref> and <xref rid="B3">Buffington and Gates (2009)</xref>. The individual images are archived at the image database at The Ohio State University (<ext-link xlink:href="purl.oclc.org/NET/hymenoptera/specimage">purl.oclc.org/NET/hymenoptera/specimage</ext-link>) with MorphBank (<ext-link xlink:href="www.morphbank.net">www.morphbank.net</ext-link>) and waspweb (<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.waspweb.org/Platygastroidea/Platygastridae/Scelioninae/Nixonia/index.htm">http://www.waspweb.org/Platygastroidea/Platygastridae/Scelioninae/Nixonia/index.htm</ext-link>). All new species have been prospectively registered with Zoobank (<xref rid="B14">Polaszek et al. 2005</xref>). Life sciences identifiers, lsids, may be resolved at the specified URLs.</p> <!-- page break --> <p>Online interactive keys were produced using Lucid and Lucid Phoenix. These keys are available at: <ext-link xlink:href="http://www.waspweb.org/Ichneumonoidea/Keys/index.htm">http://www.waspweb.org/Ichneumonoidea/Keys/index.htm</ext-link>. Users can choose between three different key formats depending on their personal preference. The key to Nixonia is available in three formats. Although Lucid Phoenix keys are interactive keys they are still dichotomous and a choice needs to be made at each key couplet to continue. Lucid matrix keys, on the other hand, use a different approach where relevant states from multiple character features can be selected independently until identification is achieved. For more information concerning Lucid keys visit <ext-link xlink:href="http://www.lucidcentral.org">http://www.lucidcentral.org</ext-link>. Files are provided as appendices in two formats enabling conversion of the Lucid matrix key to other platforms. 1. Lucid Interchange Format version 3 (LIF3) files are XML-based files that store all the Lucid3 key data, allowing exchange of the key with other key developers. 2. SDD files are XML-based files structured using the internationally agreed SDD (Structure of Descriptive Data) Schema. SDD files may be used to exchange Lucid keys with other SDD-compliant applications.</p> <p>Abbreviations and terms used in text: A1, A2, … A14: antennomere 1, 2, … 14; claval formula: distribution of the large, multiporous basiconic sensilla on the underside of apical antennomeres of the female, with the segment interval specified followed by the number of sensilla per segment (<xref rid="B1">Bin 1981</xref>); IOS: interoc­ular space, shortest distance between the inner margins of the compound eyes; LOL: lateral ocellar line, shortest distance between inner margins of median and lateral ocelli (<xref rid="B9">Masner and Huggert 1989</xref>); OOL: ocular ocellar line, shortest distance from inner orbit and outer margin of posterior ocellus (<xref rid="B9">Masner and Huggert 1989</xref>); POL: posterior ocellar line, shortest distance between inner margins of posterior ocelli (<xref rid="B9">Masner and Huggert 1989</xref>); epomial carina: the vertical portion of epo­mium on the pronotum; pronotal humeral carina: the horizontal portion of epomium on the pronotum; S1, S2, … S6: metasomatic sterna 1, 2, … 6; T1, T2, … T7: metasomatic tergum 1, 2, … 7; submarginal ridge on T1: carina dorsal and roughly parallel to the lateral margin of T1; sublateral tergal carina: longitudinal carina at the junction of dorsal and lateral faces of a metasomal tergite. Morphological terminology otherwise follows <xref rid="B10">Mikó et al. (2007)</xref>.</p> <p>Classification of vegetation (habitat association) follows <xref rid="B11">Mucina and Ruthaford (2006)</xref>.</p>  <sec><title>Depositories</title>: <p><bold>OSUC</bold>	C.A. Triplehorn Insect Collection, Columbus, OH  	<ext-link xlink:href="http://biocol.org:urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:1014">http://biocol.org:urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:1014</ext-link></p> <p><bold>SAMC</bold>	Iziko Museums of Cape Town, South Africa 	<ext-link xlink:href="http://biocol.org:urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:1018">http://biocol.org:urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:1018</ext-link></p>  <p>Accession numbers prefixed with OSUC are unique identifiers for the individual specimens, whereas numbers prefixed with SAM-HYM-P are unique identifiers for a series of specimens with the same collecting data.</p></sec></sec>  <!-- page break -->  <taxon-treatment> <nomenclature><taxon-name><taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Nixonia</taxon-name-part></taxon-name><taxon-author><string-name>Masner</string-name></taxon-author> <object-id object-id-type="lsid" xlink:href="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E56C690B-55E3-4977-B7CF-6493DEF73E6C">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E56C690B-55E3-4977-B7CF-6493DEF73E6C</object-id>  <synonymy><treatment-citation><taxon-name>Nixonia</taxon-name><mixed-citation><name><surname>Masner</surname></name>, <year>1958</year>: <fpage>101</fpage>.</mixed-citation><comment>Original description. Type: <taxon-type>Nixonia pretiosa Masner, by monotypy and original designation</taxon-type>. For subsequent taxonomic literature see <xref>Johnson (1992)</xref> or The Genera of <taxon-name>Platygastroidea</taxon-name> of the World (<ext-link xlink:href="http://purl.oclc.org/NET/hymenoptera/platygastroidea">http://purl.oclc.org/NET/hymenoptera/platygastroidea</ext-link>).</comment></treatment-citation></synonymy></nomenclature>   <treatment-sec><p><label>Diagnosis</label>. <taxon-name>Nixonia</taxon-name> is superficially similar to <taxon-name>Scelio</taxon-name> Latreille, and to the larger, more elongate species of <taxon-name>Macroteleia</taxon-name> Westwood and <taxon-name>Triteleia</taxon-name> Kieffer. <taxon-name>Nixonia</taxon-name> is distinguished by the 14­ segmented, nonclavate antennae; the strong medial propodeal tooth; and the presence of two tibial spurs on both the mid-and hind tibiae.</p></treatment-sec> <treatment-sec><p><label>Distribution</label>. <taxon-name>Nixonia</taxon-name> species richness is centered in southern Africa, but distribution extends north to Egypt, Kenya, Somalia, Rwanda, and the Democratic Republic of Congo (former Zaire). A single species, <taxon-name>N. krombeini</taxon-name>, is found in Sri Lanka, northern India, and southeast Asia (Thailand, Laos, and Vietnam). See <ext-link xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=523">http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=523</ext-link> for distribution map.</p></treatment-sec> <treatment-sec><p><label>Biology</label>. Only one species has been reared: <taxon-name>Nixonia watshami</taxon-name> a parasitoid of the eggs of <taxon-name>A. discoidalis</taxon-name> (Walker, 1869) (<taxon-name>Orthop­tera</taxon-name>: <taxon-name>Tettigoniidae</taxon-name>, <taxon-name>Hetrodinae</taxon-name>). The subfami­ly <taxon-name>Hetrodinae</taxon-name> is endemic to Africa and adjacent areas of the Arabian Peninsula (<xref rid="B13">Otte et al. 2009</xref>) and all 14 genera are likely to play hosts for <taxon-name>Nixonia</taxon-name> species. The host, however, of at least <taxon-name>N. krombeini</taxon-name> which occurs outside the range of <taxon-name>Heterodinae</taxon-name> in tropical Asia must be some other large orthopteran (<xref rid="B5">Johnson and Masner 2006</xref>).</p></treatment-sec> <treatment-sec><label>Key to species of Nixonia</label> <p>Online interactive Lucid matrix and Lucid Phoenix keys are available at: <ext-link xlink:href="http://www.waspweb.org/Platygastroidea/Keys">http://www.waspweb.org/Platygastroidea/Keys</ext-link></p>  <table-wrap><tr><td>1	</td><td>Third antennal segment shorter than, or subequal to, second antennal segment</td><td>	2</td></tr><graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2020-1-SP.tif"/><!-- page break --> <tr><td>–	</td><td>Third antennal segment longer (&gt;1.15×) than second antennal segment</td><td>	5</td></tr> <graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2021-1-SP.tif"/><tr><td>2	</td><td>Femora and tibiae yellow; eye height at least 2.5× shortest distance between eyes</td><td>	3</td></tr> <graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2022-1-SP.tif"/><tr><td>–	</td><td>Femora and tibiae reddish brown to black; eye height less than twice shortest distance between eyes</td><td>	4</td></tr> <graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2023-1-SP.tif"/><tr><td>3	</td><td>Medial portion of posterior margin of pronotum, scutellar rim, tegulae, propodeal tooth, margins of tergites 1–4, and tarsi yellow; upper mesepisternum punctuate; Namibia</td><td><taxon-name>N. flavocincta<!-- page break --></taxon-name></td></tr> <graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2024-1-SP.tif"/><tr><td>–	</td><td>Mesosoma, metasoma black without yellow markings, tarsi dark brown; upper mesepisternum longitudinally striate; Namibia</td><td><taxon-name>N. sicaria</taxon-name></td></tr> <graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2025-1-SP.tif"/><tr><td>4	</td><td>Forewings extending to middle or posterior margin of tergite 4; female metasoma with tergites 2–4 brick red, mid- and hind femora and tibiae reddish brown; South Africa</td><td><taxon-name>N. corrugata</taxon-name></td></tr> <graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2026-1-SP.tif"/><tr><td>–	</td><td>Forewings longer, extending nearly to posterior margin of tergite 5; female body and legs entirely black; South Africa</td><td><taxon-name>N. stygica</taxon-name></td></tr> <graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2027-1-SP.tif"/><tr><td>5	</td><td>Third antennal segment only slightly longer (1.15×) than second antennal segment</td><td>	6</td></tr><graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2028-1-SP.tif"/><!-- page break --> <tr><td>–	</td><td>Third antennal segment significantly longer (1.4–3.1×) than second antennal segment</td><td>	7</td></tr> <graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2029-1-SP.tif"/><tr><td>6	</td><td>Occipital carina not developed; female tergite 6 irregularly carinate; female body and legs entirely black; South Africa</td><td><taxon-name>N. elongata</taxon-name></td></tr> <graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2030-1-SP.tif"/><tr><td>–	</td><td>Occipital carina massive; female tergite 6 longitudinally carinate; female metasomatic segments 2–5 brick red; legs, except coxae, reddish orange; South Africa, Botswana</td><td><taxon-name>N. pecki</taxon-name></td></tr> <graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2031-1-SP.tif"/><tr><td>7	</td><td>Maxillary palpomere 4 cylindrical; mandible long, with lower tooth either absent or much shorter than upper, base of mandible with dense tuft of thick setae</td><td>	8</td></tr><graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2032-1-SP.tif"/><!-- page break --> <tr><td>–	</td><td>Maxillary palpomere 4 with strongly expanded lateral lobe, width of palpomere nearly equal to its length; mandible short, bidentate, lower tooth only slightly shorter than upper, base of mandible without dense tuft of thick setae</td><td>	10</td></tr> <graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2033-1-SP.tif"/><tr><td>8	</td><td>Mandible unidentate, with no indication of lower tooth; legs orange-yellow; Somalia</td><td><taxon-name>N. bini</taxon-name></td></tr> <graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2034-1-SP.tif"/><tr><td>–	</td><td>Mandible with short, but distinct lower tooth; legs black</td><td>	9 </td></tr> <graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2035-1-SP.tif"/><tr><td>9	</td><td>Mesoscutum and scutellum with irregular, sharply defined rugulosities, with small setigerous punctures scattered over surface; tegula reddish brown, distinctly lighter in color than mesoscutum; Egypt</td><td><taxon-name>N. priesneri</taxon-name></td></tr><graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2036-1-SP.tif"/><!-- page break --> <tr><td>–	</td><td>Mesoscutum and scutellum covered by deep, confluent, large setigerous punctures; tegula black, concolorous with mesoscutum; Angola, Congo, Kenya, Malawi, Rwanda, Zimbabwe</td><td><taxon-name>N. atra</taxon-name></td></tr> <graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2037-1-SP.tif"/><tr><td>10	</td><td>Propodeal tooth cordate to subcordate, sides convex, longitudinally carinate, with or without medial depression; scutellum longitudinally striate; female tergite 6 deeply, emarginate posteromedially; large, 9 mm in length; South Africa</td><td>	11</td></tr> <graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2038-1-SP.tif"/><tr><td>–	</td><td>Propodeal tooth with sides straight, and pointed or ligulate, usually with deep medial depression; scutellum areolate-punctate; female tergite 6 with only shallow emargination posteromedially; moderate in size, 5–7 mm in length</td><td>	12</td></tr> <graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2039-1-SP.tif"/><tr><td>11	</td><td>Fore- and midtibiae with numerous stout, semi-erect, dark spines over outer surface; propodeal tooth without depression; female tergite 6 deeply, narrowly emarginate posteromedially, lateral flanges narrow</td><td><taxon-name>N. gigas</taxon-name></td></tr><graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2040-1-SP.tif"/><!-- page break --> <tr><td>–	</td><td>Fore and midtibiae at most with small, semi-appressed spines; propodeal tooth with posterior-medial depression; female tergite 6 with deep, broad emargination posterio-medially, lateral flanges wide and conspicuous</td><td><taxon-name>N. mcgregori</taxon-name></td></tr> <graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2041-1-SP.tif"/><tr><td>12	</td><td>Eye height distinctly greater than shortest distance between eyes; mesoscutum with scattered punctures and wide interstices with dense mat microsculpture; India, Laos, Sri Lanka, Thailand, Vietnam</td><td><taxon-name>N. krombeini</taxon-name></td></tr> <graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2042-1-SP.tif"/><tr><td>–	</td><td>Eye height sub-equal to, or only slightly greater, than shortest distance between eyes; mesoscutum with dense large punctures and narrow interstices with shining surface; Africa</td><td>	13</td></tr> <graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2043-1-SP.tif"/><tr><td>13	</td><td>Shortest distance between eyes 0.9× eye height; forewing with several streaks of heavy infuscation; body length 7–10 mm; South Africa</td><td>	14</td></tr><graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2044-1-SP.tif"/><!-- page break --> <tr><td>–	</td><td>Shortest distance between eyes equal to eye height; forewing with only moderate streaks of infuscation; body length 5.0–5.5 mm</td><td>	15</td></tr> <graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2045-1-SP.tif"/><tr><td>14	</td><td>Mesoscutum wider than long; scape elongate (3× longer than wide); dense field of setae obvious on vertex in anterior view; pronotal shoulders rounded</td><td><taxon-name>N. lamorali</taxon-name></td></tr> <graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2046-1-SP.tif"/><tr><td>–	</td><td>Mesoscutum as wide as long; scape expanded (2.5× longer than wide); setae sparse on vertex; pronotal shoulders subquadrate</td><td><taxon-name>N. masneri</taxon-name></td></tr> <graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2047-1-SP.tif"/><tr><td>15	</td><td>Mesosoma, antennae, and legs entirely dark brown to black; Botswana, Namibia, Zimbabwe</td><td><taxon-name>N. watshami</taxon-name></td></tr><graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2048-1-SP.tif"/><!-- page break --> <tr><td>–	</td><td>Pronotum, mesonotum, antennomeres 1–3, and legs beyond coxae deep orange to reddish brown; Namibia</td><td><taxon-name>N. pretiosa</taxon-name></td></tr><graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2049-1-SP.tif"/></table-wrap></treatment-sec></taxon-treatment>   <taxon-treatment><nomenclature><taxon-name><taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Nixonia</taxon-name-part><taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">masneri</taxon-name-part></taxon-name><taxon-author><string-name>van Noort &amp; Johnson</string-name></taxon-author>, <taxon-status>sp. n.</taxon-status> <object-id object-id-type="lsid" xlink:href="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:51495B19-AA60-4560-AAC6-2EED4110C0ED">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:51495B19-AA60-4560-AAC6-2EED4110C0ED</object-id> <xref>Figures 1A–F</xref></nomenclature>  <materials-examined><p><label>Type material</label>. <typeStatus>Holotype</typeStatus><individualCount>1</individualCount><sex>male</sex>. <country>SOUTH AFRICA</country>, <stateProvince>Western Cape</stateProvince>, <locality>Kogelberg Nature Reserve</locality>, <verbatimCoordinates><verbatimLatitude>34°16.481’S</verbatimLatitude><verbatimLongitude>19°01.033’E</verbatimLongitude></verbatimCoordinates>, <verbatimEventDate>16 Jan–16 Feb 2000</verbatimEventDate>, <recordedBy>S. van Noort</recordedBy>, <samplingProtocol>Malaise trap, KO98-M53</samplingProtocol>, <locationRemarks>Mesic Mountain Fynbos, last burnt c. 1978</locationRemarks>, <collectionCode>SAM-HYM-P025052</collectionCode>, <catalogNumber>OSUC 256956</catalogNumber> (<institutionCode>SAMC</institutionCode>). <typeStatus>Paratypes</typeStatus>: <individualCount>2</individualCount> <sex>males</sex>, same data <collectionCode>SAM-HYM-P025052</collectionCode>, <catalogNumber>OSUC 256940</catalogNumber> (<institutionCode>SAMC</institutionCode>, <institutionCode>OSUC</institutionCode>); 1 male: <country>South Africa</country>, <stateProvince>Northern Cape</stateProvince>, <locality>Avontuur Farm, 16km NW Nieuwoudtville</locality>, <verbatimElevation>764m</verbatimElevation>, <verbatimCoordinates>31°16.249'S 19°02.900'E</verbatimCoordinates>, <verbatimEventDate>25 Dec 2008–27 Jan 2009</verbatimEventDate>, <recordedBy>S van Noort</recordedBy>, <samplingProtocol>Malaise trap, GL07-FYN1-M73</samplingProtocol>, <locationRemarks>Bokkeveld Sandstone Fynbos</locationRemarks>, <collectionCode>SAM-HYM-P030242</collectionCode>, <catalogNumber>OSUC 268382</catalogNumber> (<institutionCode>SAMC</institutionCode>).</p></materials-examined> <treatment-sec><p><label>Diagnosis</label>. Most similar to <taxon-name>Nixonia lamorali</taxon-name>, distinguished by the mesoscutum which is as wide as long; a more expanded scape (2.5× longer than wide); lack of setae on the vertex; occipital carina present dorsally; and pronotal shoulders that are subquadrate. </p></treatment-sec> <treatment-sec><p><label>Etymology</label>. Named in honour of Lubomír Masner, who with his enthusiasm and dedication to the discovery and description of parasitic wasp species, has inspired passion in numerous protégés to catalogue the incredible hyper-diversity of the micro world.</p></treatment-sec> <treatment-sec><p><label>Distribution and habitat association</label>. Currently only known from two widely spaced localities: Kogelberg Nature Reserve in the Western Cape Province and Avontuur Farm in the Northern Cape Province <xref>(Fig 3)</xref>. The species is associated with the Fynbos biome and is thus likely to be present over a much larger area than currently recorded (the extent of the Fynbos biome is depicted in <xref>Fig 3)</xref>. Distribution map available at <ext-link xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/index.html?id=247388">http://hol.osu.edu/index.html?id=247388</ext-link>. </p></treatment-sec> <description><p><label>Description</label>: Holotype male. Length: 8.5 mm; completely black, mandibles usually black, but may be reddish-brown <xref>(figs 1A, B)</xref>; wings infuscate throughout, brownish. </p> <p>Head <xref>(figs. 1C-E)</xref> transverse in dorsal view, width 1.5× length; vertex rugulose-punctate, shining; OOL short, lateral ocellus separated from inner orbit by a third of ocellar diameter; POL 1.6× LOL; occiput rugulose-punctate, with reticulate microsculpture; occipital carina weakly developed dorsally; frons rugulose-punctate, shining, above toruli with few transverse wrinkles medially; frons somewhat narrow, IOS 0.9× greatest length of eye; toruli closely approximated, separated by distance less<!-- page break --> than half torulus diameter, frons between toruli not projecting, flat; rim of torulus evenly raised; apical margin of clypeus with blunt medial projection; position of malar sulcus demarcated by fine granulate microsculpture; sculpture of cheeks laterad of malar area rugose-punctate, with distinct longitudinal sculpture; mandible short, bidentate, upper tooth only slightly longer than lower, without dense basal tuft of setae; maxillary palpal segment 4 distinctly expanded medially, subtriangular; A1 finely reticulate, 2.5× longer than wide, greatest width beyond apical 0.6 of segment; length of A3 1.5× length of A2. </p><!-- page break --> <fig-group><caption><bold>Figure 1.</bold><taxon-name>Nixonia masneri</taxon-name> van Noort &amp; Johnson, sp. n., male, holotype. <bold>A</bold> habitus, lateral view <bold>B</bold> habitus, dorsal view <bold>C</bold> head, mesosoma, lateral view <bold>D</bold> mesosoma, dorsal view <bold>E</bold> head, anterior view <bold>F</bold> metasoma dorsal view. Scale bars in millimeters. (<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.morphbank.net/?id=999008676">http://www.morphbank.net/?id=999008676</ext-link>)</caption><graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-969-1-SP.tif"/></fig-group><p>Mesosoma <xref>(figs. 1 C,D)</xref> as high as wide, length 1.4× height in lateral view; pronotal shoulders coarsely punctate; lateral surface of pronotum coarsely punctate; ne­trion punctuate-rugulose with weak longitudinal striation; mesoscutum deeply punctate, with broad interstices; parapsidal lines absent; scutellum coarsely punctate, with fine microsculpture on posterior margin; median propodeal tooth subcordate, sides straight, length 1.4× maximum width, pointed apically, with median excavation bounded by lateral longitudinal carina; upper mesepisternum with strong longitudinal sculpture; fine foveae separating mesepister­num and mesepimeron extending from base of wing to coxal cavity; lower mesepisternum finely reticulate-punctate; mesepimeral hook smooth; tegula finely punctate; apex of forewing extending to apex of T4; fore and mid tibiae with fine, semidecum­bent spines on outer surface. </p> <p>Metasoma <xref>(figs. 1A,B,F)</xref> 3.7× longer than greatest width; T1 1.4× wider than long; T1–T4 longitudinally rugose.</p></description> </taxon-treatment>  <taxon-treatment><nomenclature><taxon-name><taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Nixonia</taxon-name-part><taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">mcgregori</taxon-name-part></taxon-name><taxon-author><string-name>van Noort &amp; Johnson</string-name></taxon-author>, <taxon-status>sp. n.</taxon-status> <object-id xlink:href="urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:8BC4BB9E-7CC8-4006-8399-34DD54CD40FB" object-id-type="lsid">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:8BC4BB9E-7CC8-4006-8399-34DD54CD40FB</object-id> <xref>Figures 2A-F</xref></nomenclature>  <materials-examined><p><label>Type material</label>. Holotype female. SOUTH AFRICA, Northern Cape, Hantam National Botanical Garden, 758m, 31°24.293'S 19°09.215'E, 10 Dec 2007 – 13 Jan<!-- page break --> 2008, S van Noort, Malaise trap, GL07-DOL2-M05, Nieuwoudtville-Roggeveld Dolerite Renosterveld, SAM-HYM-P025051, OSUC 256957 (SAMC). Paratypes: 2 females, 1 male, SOUTH AFRICA, Northern Cape, Hantam National Botanical Garden, 787m, 31°24.845'S 19°09.443'E, 10 Dec 2007–13 Jan 2008, S van Noort, Malaise trap, GL07-KOP1-M06, Nieuwoudtville Dolerite Koppie Renosterveld, SAM-HYM-P025049, OSUC 256941 (SAMC, OSUC). 2 males, South Africa, Northern Cape, Hantam National Botanical Garden, 752m, 31°23.802'S<fig-group><caption><bold>Figure 3.</bold> Distribution and habitat association of <taxon-name>Nixonia masneri</taxon-name> and <taxon-name>N. mcgregori</taxon-name>. Biome map from <xref rid="B15">Rutherford et al. (2006)</xref>.</caption><graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-2019-1-SP.tif"/></fig-group><fig-group><caption><bold>Figure 2.</bold><taxon-name>Nixonia mcgregori</taxon-name> van Noort &amp; Johnson, sp. n., female, holotype. <bold>A</bold> habitus, lateral view <bold>B</bold> habitus, dorsal view <bold>C</bold> head, mesosoma, lateral view <bold>D</bold> mesosoma, dorsal view <bold>E</bold> head, anterior view <bold>F</bold> metasoma dorsal view. Scale bars in millimeters. (<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.morphbank.net/?id=999008677">http://www.morphbank.net/?id=999008677</ext-link>)</caption><graphic href="file:///D:/Work/ZOOKEYS/ZooKeys%2020%202009%20Masner/112/112-970-1-SP.tif"/></fig-group><!-- page break --> 19°08.799'E, 10 Dec 2007–13 Jan 2008, S van Noort, Malaise trap, GL07-REN1-M01, Nieuwoudtville Shale Renosterveld, SAM-HYM-P025050 (SAMC). 1 female, 2 males, South Africa, Northern Cape, Hantam National Botanical Garden, 755m, 31°24.274'S 19°09.164'E, 10 Dec 2007 – 13 Jan 2008, S van Noort, Malaise trap, GL07-DOL1-M04, Nieuwoudtville-Roggeveld Dolerite Renosterveld, SAM-HYM-P025047 (SAMC). 7 males South Africa, Northern Cape, Hantam National Botanical Garden, 797m, 31°24.841'S 19°09.551'E, 10 Dec 2007 – 13 Jan 2008, S van Noort, Malaise trap, GL07-KOP2-M07, Nieuwoudtville Dolerite Koppie Renosterveld, SAM-HYM-P025048, OSUC 256942 (SAMC, OSUC). 1 male, South Africa, Northern Cape, Hantam National Botanical Garden, 741m, 31°24.182'S 19°08.587'E, 13 Jan – 14 February 2008, S van Noort, Malaise trap, GL07-REN3-M10, Nieuwoudtville Shale Renosterveld, SAM-HYM-P025054 (SAMC). 4 females, 7 males, South Africa, Northern Cape, Hantam National Botanical Garden, 787m, 31°24.845'S 19°09.443'E, 13 Jan – 14 February 2008, S van Noort, Malaise trap, GL07-KOP1-M13, Nieuwoudtville Dolerite Koppie Renosterveld, SAM-HYM-P025055, OSUC 256943, OSUC 256944 (SAMC, OSUC). 2 females, 9 males, South Africa, Northern Cape, Hantam National Botanical Garden, 797m, 31°24.841'S 19°09.551'E, 13 Jan – 14 February 2008, S van Noort, Malaise trap, GL07-KOP2-M14, Nieuwoudtville Dolerite Koppie Renosterveld, SAM-HYM-P025056, OSUC 256945, OSUC 256946 (SAMC, OSUC). 1 male, South Africa, Northern Cape, Avontuur Farm, 16km NW Nieuwoudtville, 764m, 31°16.249'S 19°02.900'E, 25 Dec 2008 – 27 Jan 2009, S van Noort, Malaise trap, GL07-FYN1-M73, Bokkeveld Sandstone Fynbos, SAM-HYM-P030249 (SAMC). 1 female, same data except: Yellow Pan trap, GL07-FYN1-Y34, SAM-HYM-P030243 (SAMC). 1 female, same data except: Yellow Pan trap, GL07-FYN1-Y35, SAM-HYM-P030244 (SAMC). 1 male, South Africa, Northern Cape, Hantam National Botanical Garden, 49m, 31°20.602'S 19°11.695'E, 25 Dec 2008 – 27 Jan 2009, S van Noort, Malaise trap, GL07-SUC1-M74, Hantam Succulent Karoo, SAM-HYM-P030245 (SAMC). 1 male, same data except for: Yellow pan trap, GL07-SUC1-Y37, SAM-HYM-P030246 (SAMC).</p></materials-examined> <treatment-sec><p><label>Diagnosis</label>: <taxon-name>Nixonia mcgregori</taxon-name> is distinguished by the deep and broad emargination posterior-medially on T6 and the wide and conspicuous lateral flanges. It is most similar to <taxon-name>N. gigas</taxon-name>, but <taxon-name>N. gigas</taxon-name> has a very narrow excision in the female T6 and strong spines on the fore-and midtibiae.</p></treatment-sec> <treatment-sec><p><label>Etymology</label>. Named in honour of conservationist Neil McGregor, former owner of Glenlyon farm. Neil’s farm has formed the core of the recently established Hantam National Botanical Garden at Nieuwoudtville.</p></treatment-sec> <treatment-sec><p><label>Distribution and habitat association</label>. <taxon-name>Nixonia mcgregori</taxon-name> is currently only known from the vicinity of Nieuwoudtville in the Northern Cape Province where it is associated with the Succulent Karoo and Fynbos biomes (Fig 3). The species has been sampled in four Fynbos vegetation types: Nieuwoudtville-Roggeveld Dolerite Renosterveld; Nieuwoudtville Dolerite Koppie Renosterveld, Nieuwoudtville Shale Renosterveld and Bokkeveld Sandstone Fynbos, as well as in the Hantam Succulent Karoo. Distribution map available at: http://hol.osu.edu/index.html?id=247389.</p></treatment-sec> <description><p><label>Description</label>. Holotype female. Length 7.0 mm; completely black, tarsi lighter (figs. 2A, B); wings infuscate throughout, brownish (fig. 2F). </p> <p>Head (figs. 2C-E) transverse in dorsal view, width 1.8× length; vertex medially smooth, shining with very fine setiforous punctures, laterally rugulose-punctate, shining or completely rugulose-punctate, shining; OOL short, lateral ocellus in close apposition with compound eye, separated from inner orbit by a quarter of ocellar diameter; POL 1.4× LOL; occiput rugulose-punctate, shining; occipital carina not discernable; frons rugulose-punctate, shining, above toruli with strong transverse striation; frons somewhat narrow, IOS 0.87× great­est length of eye; toruli in close apposition separated by 0.14× diameter of torulus; frons between toruli not projecting, flat; rim of torulus raised dorsally and venatrally; apical margin of clypeus with medial blunt tooth; area below eye (in normal position of malar sulcus) with fine granulate microsculpture; cheeks laterad of malar area rugose-punctate, with longitudinal sculpture; mandible short, bidentate, upper tooth only slightly longer than lower, without dense basal tuft of setae; maxillary palpal segment 4 distinctly expanded medially, sub-triangular; A1 finely reticulate, greatest width in apical two-thirds of segment 3.9× longer than wide; length of A3 1.6× length of A2. </p> <p>Mesosoma (figs. 2A, D) as high as wide, length 1.3× height; pronotal shoulders coarsely punctate; lateral surface of pronotum coarsely punctate; netrion punctuate-rugulose with strong longitudinal striation; mesoscu­tum deeply punctate; parapsidal lines absent; scu­tellum: coarsely rugulose-punctate, with longitudinal elements; median propodeal tooth subcordate, broad, length 1.1× maximum width, rounded apically, longitudi­nally striate except for smooth posterior-medial excavation; upper mesepisternum with strong longitudinal sculpture; fine foveae separating mesepisternum and mesepimeron extending from base of wing to coxal cavity; lower mesepisternum finely reticulate-punc-tate; mesepimeral hook longitudinally keeled; tegula finely punctate; R1 in forewing distinct­ly separated from costal margin, extending only halfway from R to margin; apex of forewing extending to mid or apex of T5; R in hindwing with tracheate section long, nearly reaching hamuli; outer surface of tibiae with fine, semidecum­bent spines. </p> <p>Metasoma (figs. 2A,B,F) 2.9× longer than greatest width; T1 twice as wide as long; terga longitudinally rugose; female T6 with broad, deep apical emargination, depth equivalent to width, lateral flange broad; T6 anteromedially with distinctive field of microsculpture.</p> </description><treatment-sec><p><label>Biology</label>. Given that one species of <taxon-name>Nixonia</taxon-name>, <taxon-name>N. watshami</taxon-name>, has been recorded as an egg parasitoid of an armoured ground cricket, <taxon-name>A. discoidalis</taxon-name>, in Namibia and Botswana it is plausible that <taxon-name>N. mcgregori</taxon-name> and <taxon-name>N. corrugata</taxon-name> may be egg parasitoids of the armoured ground cricket species, <taxon-name>Hetrodes pupus</taxon-name> (Linnaeus, 1758) that is very common in the habitats where these two species of <taxon-name>Nixonia </taxon-name>occur.</p></treatment-sec></taxon-treatment><!-- page break --> <sec><title>Additional distribution records for described species</title> <sec><taxon-name>Nixonia corrugata</taxon-name> Johnson &amp; Masner, 2006  Distribution map available at: <ext-link xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/index.html?id=184918">http://hol.osu.edu/index.html?id=184918</ext-link>  <p><individualCount>1</individualCount><sex>male</sex>, <country>South Africa</country>, <stateProvince>Northern Cape</stateProvince>, <locality>Hantam National Botanical Garden</locality>, <verbatimElevation>787m</verbatimElevation>, 31°24.845'S 19°09.443'E, 7–10 December 2007, <recordedBy>S van Noort</recordedBy>, <samplingProtocol>Yellow pan trap, GL07-KOP1-Y02</samplingProtocol>, <locationRemarks>Niewoudtville Dolerite Koppie Renosterveld</locationRemarks>, <collectionCode>SAM-HYM-P025046</collectionCode>, <catalogNumber>OSUC 256947</catalogNumber> (<institutionCode>SAMC</institutionCode>). <individualCount>1</individualCount> <sex>female</sex>, <individualCount>1</individualCount> <sex>male</sex>, <country>South Africa</country>, <stateProvince>Northern Cape</stateProvince>, <locality>Hantam National Botanical Garden</locality>, <verbatimElevation>741m</verbatimElevation>, <verbatimCoordinates>31°24.182'S 19°08.587'E</verbatimCoordinates>, <verbatimEventDate>10 Dec 2007 – 13 Jan 2008</verbatimEventDate>, <recordedBy>S van Noort</recordedBy>, <samplingProtocol>Malaise trap, GL07-REN3-M03</samplingProtocol>, <locationRemarks>Nieuwoudtville Shale Renosterveld</locationRemarks>, <collectionCode>SAM-HYM-P025045</collectionCode>, <catalogNumber>OSUC 256948</catalogNumber>, <catalogNumber>OSUC 256949</catalogNumber> (<institutionCode>SAMC</institutionCode>); <individualCount>1</individualCount> <sex>female</sex>, <individualCount>2</individualCount> <sex>males</sex>, same data except for <verbatimEventDate>13 Jan – 14 February 2008</verbatimEventDate>, <samplingProtocol>GL07-REN3-M10</samplingProtocol>, <collectionCode>SAM-HYM-P025053</collectionCode>, <catalogNumber>OSUC 256950</catalogNumber>, <catalogNumber>OSUC 256951</catalogNumber>, <catalogNumber>OSUC 256952</catalogNumber> (<institutionCode>SAMC</institutionCode>); <individualCount>1</individualCount> <sex>male</sex>, same data except for <verbatimEventDate>18 November – 25 Dec 2008</verbatimEventDate>, <samplingProtocol>Yellow pan trap, GL07-REN3-Y18</samplingProtocol>, <collectionCode>SAM-HYM-P030247</collectionCode>, <catalogNumber>OSUC 256953</catalogNumber> (<institutionCode>SAMC</institutionCode>).</p></sec>   <sec><taxon-name>Nixonia lamorali</taxon-name> Johnson &amp; Masner, 2006 Distribution map available at: <ext-link xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/index.html?id=184923">http://hol.osu.edu/index.html?id=184923</ext-link>  <p><individualCount>1</individualCount><sex>male</sex>, <country>South Africa</country>, <stateProvince>Western Cape</stateProvince>, <locality>Langberg Farm, (3 km 270° W Langebaanweg)</locality>, <verbatimCoordinates>32°58.461’S 18°07.344’E</verbatimCoordinates>, <verbatimEventDate>12–19 Mar 2003</verbatimEventDate>, <recordedBy>S. van Noort</recordedBy>, <samplingProtocol>Malaise trap, LW02-N2-M175</samplingProtocol>, <locationRemarks>Sand Plain Fynbos</locationRemarks>, <collectionCode>SAM-HYM-P030184</collectionCode>, <catalogNumber>OSUC 256954</catalogNumber> (<institutionCode>SAMC</institutionCode>).</p></sec>   <sec><taxon-name>Nixonia stygica</taxon-name> Johnson &amp; Masner, 2006 Distribution map available at: <ext-link xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/index.html?id=184926">http://hol.osu.edu/index.html?id=184926</ext-link>  <individualCount>1</individualCount> <sex>female</sex>, <country>South Africa</country>, <stateProvince>Western Cape</stateProvince>, <locality>Gamkaberg Nature Reserve</locality>, <verbatimCoordinates>33°39.941'S 21°53.505'E</verbatimCoordinates>, <verbatimElevation>760m</verbatimElevation>, <verbatimEventDate>23.XII.2008–16.I.2009</verbatimEventDate>, <recordedBy>S. van Noort</recordedBy>, <samplingProtocol>Malaise trap, GB09-SUC1-M01</samplingProtocol>, <locationRemarks>Succulent Karoo/ Riverine vegetation ecotone</locationRemarks>, <collectionCode>SAM-HYM-P030248</collectionCode>, <catalogNumber>OSUC 256955</catalogNumber> (<institutionCode>SAMC</institutionCode>).</sec></sec>
	</body> 
	<back>
		<ack>
			<label>Acknowledgements</label> 
			<p>Thanks to Bettina Koelle and Shannon Parring (Indigo Development and Change), Eugene Marinus (SANBI), and Tom and Lisl Barry (Cape Nature) for providing logistical support; and to Aisha Mayekiso, Nosiphiwo Goci and Mmamotswa Mosweu for their dedication to processing samples. The South African National Biodiversity Institute provided permission to conduct research in the Hantam National Botanical Garden. Table Mountain Fund and WWF-SA provided permission to conduct research<!-- page break --> on Avontuur Farm. Northern Cape Nature Conservation and Cape Nature (Western Cape Province) granted collecting permits. This material is based upon work supported by the National Science Foundation under grant No. DEB–0614764 to N.F. Johnson and A.D. Austin, and by a South African National Research Foundation grant GUN 61497 to S. van Noort, and an Italian/South African Scientific and Technological Co-operation grant GUN 2068865 to S. van Noort and M. Olmi (University of Tuscia).</p> 
		</ack>
		<ref-list>References 
			<ref id="B1">
				<element-citation>
					<person-group>
						<name>
							<surname>Bin</surname>
							<given-names>F</given-names>
						</name>
					</person-group> 
					(<year>1981</year>) 
					<article-title>Definition of female antennal clava based on its plate sensilla in <taxon-name>Hymenoptera</taxon-name> <taxon-name>Scelionidae</taxon-name> <taxon-name>Telenominae</taxon-name></article-title>. 
					<source>Redia</source> 
					<volume>64</volume>: 
					<fpage>245</fpage>–
					<lpage>261</lpage>. 
				</element-citation>
			</ref> 
			<ref id="B2"><element-citation><person-group><name><surname>Buffington</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burks</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McNeil</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Advanced techniques for imaging microhymenoptera</article-title>. <source>American Entomologist</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>50</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.</element-citation></ref> <ref id="B3"><element-citation><person-group><name><surname>Buffington</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gates</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Advanced imaging techniques II: using a compound microscope for photographing point-mount specimens</article-title>. <source>American Entomologist</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>222</fpage>–<lpage>224</lpage>.</element-citation></ref> <ref id="B4"><element-citation><person-group><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Catalog of world <taxon-name>Proc­totrupoidea</taxon-name> excluding <taxon-name>Platygastridae</taxon-name></article-title>. <source>Mem­oirs of the American Entomological Institute</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>825</lpage>.</element-citation></ref> <ref id="B5"><element-citation><person-group><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Masner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Revision of world species of the genus <taxon-name>Nixonia</taxon-name> Masner (<taxon-name>Hymenoptera</taxon-name>: <taxon-name>Platygastroidea</taxon-name>, <taxon-name>Scelionidae</taxon-name>)</article-title>. <source>American Museum Novitates</source> <volume>3518</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.</element-citation></ref> <ref id="B6"><element-citation><person-group><name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Buffington</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Dome lighting for insect imaging under a microscope</article-title>. <source>American Entomologist</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>198</fpage>–<lpage>200</lpage>.</element-citation></ref> <ref id="B7"><element-citation><person-group><name><surname>Masner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1958</year>) <article-title>An interesting new genus of <taxon-name>Scelionidae</taxon-name> from S.W. Africa (<taxon-name>Hymenoptera</taxon-name>: <taxon-name>Proctotrupoidea</taxon-name>)</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the Royal Entomological Society of London</source> (<series>B</series>) <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>101</fpage>–<lpage>104</lpage>. </element-citation></ref> <ref id="B8"><element-citation><person-group><name><surname>Masner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1970</year>) <article-title>A new species of <taxon-name>Nixonia</taxon-name> Masner from Rhodesia</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the Ento­mological Society of Washington</source> <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>90</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>. </element-citation></ref> <ref id="B9"><element-citation><person-group><name><surname>Masner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huggert</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>World review and keys to genera of the subfamily <taxon-name>Inostemmatinae</taxon-name> with reassignment of the taxa to the <taxon-name>Platygastrinae</taxon-name> and <taxon-name>Sceliotrachelinae</taxon-name> (<taxon-name>Hyme­noptera</taxon-name>: <taxon-name>Platygastridae</taxon-name>)</article-title>. <source>Memoirs of the Entomological Society of Canada</source> <volume>147</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>214</lpage>. </element-citation></ref> <ref id="B10"><element-citation><person-group><name><surname>Mikó</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vilhelmsen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Masner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pénzes</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Skeletomusculature of <taxon-name>Scelionidae</taxon-name> (<taxon-name>Hymenoptera</taxon-name>: <taxon-name>Platygastroidea</taxon-name>): head and mesosoma</article-title>. <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>1571</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>. (<ext-link>http://www.mapress.com/zootaxa/2007f/zt01571p078.pdf</ext-link>).</element-citation></ref> <ref id="B11"><element-citation><person-group><name><surname>Mucina</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rutherford</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <year>2006</year>. <source>The vegetation of South Africa, Lesotho and Swaziland</source>. <publisher>SANBI</publisher>, <publisher-loc>Pretoria</publisher-loc>, <lpage>807</lpage> pp. </element-citation></ref> <ref id="B12"><element-citation><person-group><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dowton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Phylogeny of the platygastroid wasps (<taxon-name>Hymenoptera</taxon-name>) based on sequences from the 18S rRNA, 28S rRNA and cytochrome oxidase genes: implications for the evolution of the ovipositor system and host relationships</article-title>. <source>Biological Journal of the Linnean Society</source> <volume>91</volume>: <fpage>653</fpage>–<lpage>669</lpage>.</element-citation></ref> <ref id="B13"><element-citation><person-group><name><surname>Otte</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eades</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cigliano</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Naskrecki</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>.</person-group><source><taxon-name>Orthop­tera</taxon-name> Species File Online</source>. Version 2.2. <ext-link>http://osf2.orthoptera.org</ext-link>. [accessed: 23 February, <year>2009</year>]</element-citation></ref> <ref id="B14"><element-citation><person-group><name><surname>Polaszek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Agosti</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alonso-Zarazaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beccaloni</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Place Bjørn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bouchet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brothers</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name>Earl of Cranbrook</name>, <name><surname>Evenhuis</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Godfray</surname><given-names>HCJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krell</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lipscomb</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lyal</surname><given-names>CHC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mace</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mawatari</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Minelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>PKL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Patterson</surname><!-- page break --><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pyle</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rogo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Taverne</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Tol</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>QD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>A universal register for animal names</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>437</volume>: <fpage>477</fpage>.</element-citation></ref> <ref id="B15"><element-citation><person-group><name><surname>Rutherford</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mucina</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Powrie</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Biomes and bioregions of Southern Africa<chapter-title/></article-title>. In: <name><surname>Mucina</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rutherford</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>The vegetation of South Africa, Lesotho and Swaziland</source>. <publisher><publisher-name>SANBI</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Pretoria</publisher-loc></publisher>, <fpage>30</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.</element-citation></ref> <ref id="B16"><element-citation><person-group><name><surname>Sharkey</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Phylogeny and classification of <taxon-name>Hymenoptera</taxon-name></article-title>. In: <person-group><name xlink:role="editor"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z-Q</given-names></name>, <name xlink:role="editor"><surname>Shear</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <issue-title>Linnaeus tercentenary: progress in invertebrate taxonomy</issue-title>. <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>1668</volume>: <fpage>521</fpage>–<lpage>548</lpage>. (<ext-link>http://mapress.com/zootaxa/2007f/zt01668p548.pdf</ext-link>).</element-citation></ref> <ref id="B17"><element-citation><person-group><name><surname>van Noort</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>South African survey reveals further <taxon-name>Nixonia</taxon-name> gems</article-title>. <source>Skaphion</source> <volume>2</volume>(<issue>13</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>3</lpage>.</element-citation></ref></ref-list><!-- page break --><sec><treatment-sec><label>Appendix 1</label>. <supplementary-material content-type="Lucid3"><caption>Lucid Interchange Format version 3 (LIF3) file to the species of Nixonia (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae).</caption><long-desc>This is an XML-based file that stores all the Lucid3 key data, allowing exchange of the key with other key developers. <object-id object-id-type="doi" xlink:xref="doi:10.3897/zookeys.20.112.app.1.ik">doi:10.3897/zookeys.20.112.app.1.ik</object-id>.</long-desc>  <permissions><material-citation>Copyright notice: This dataset is made available under the Open Database License (<ext-link xlink:xref="http://opendatacommons.org/licenses/odbl/1.0/">http://opendatacommons.org/licenses/odbl/1.0/</ext-link>). The Open Database License (ODbL) is a license agreement intended to allow users to freely share, modify, and use this Dataset while maintaining this same freedom for others, provided that the original source and author(s) are credited. </material-citation></permissions>  <attrib><material-citation>Citation: van Noort S, Johnson NF (2009) Lucid Interchange Format version 3 (LIF3) file to the species of Nixonia (Hymenoptera: Platygastridae). doi:10.3897/zookeys.20.112.app.1.ik. Dataset published in: Zookeys 20: 31–51. doi:10.3897/zookeys.20.112</material-citation></attrib></supplementary-material> </treatment-sec><treatment-sec><label>Appendix 2</label>. <supplementary-material content-type="Lucid SDD"><caption>Lucid SDD file to the species of Nixonia (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae).</caption><long-desc>This is a XML-based file structured using the internationally agreed SDD (Structure of Descriptive Data) Schema. This SDD file may be used to exchange the Lucid key with other SDD-compliant applications. <object-id object-id-type="doi" xlink:xref="doi:10.3897/zookeys.20.112.app.2.ik">doi:10.3897/zookeys.20.112.app.2.ik</object-id>.</long-desc>  <permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright notice: This dataset is made available under the Open Database License (<ext-link xlink:xref="http://opendatacommons.org/licenses/odbl/1.0/">http://opendatacommons.org/licenses/odbl/1.0/</ext-link>). The Open Database License (ODbL) is a license agreement intended to allow users to freely share, modify, and use this Dataset while maintaining this same freedom for others, provided that the original source and author(s) are credited.</copyright-statement></permissions>   <attrib><material-citation>Citation: van Noort S, Johnson NF (2009) Lucid SDD file to the species of Nixonia (Hymenoptera: Platygastridae). doi:10.3897/zookeys.20.112.app.2.ik. Dataset published in: Zookeys 20: 31–51. doi:10.3897/zookeys.20.112</material-citation></attrib></supplementary-material></treatment-sec> </sec>
	</back>
</article>
</Root>
